Guide to the McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center Vertical File, 1948-1991
The John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- Advertising Series (ADV), 23 Boxes
  - ADV 50. TECHNIQUES
    - ADV 50:4 Copy-Approaches and Themes
      - 50:4-3 Specific Approaches and Themes
        - [Essay-Advertisements--see: ADV 50:4-3.12.1, Advertorials/Special Sections]
        - [Ethnics in copy/commercials--see: ADV 50:4-3.23, Minorities/Ethnics in Copy/Commercials]
        - 50:4-3.15 Financial
        - 50:4-3.16 Generic
        - 50:4-3.17 Hidden Product
        - 50:4-3.18 Historical (comparisons with ads of yesteryear)
        - 50:4-3.19 House Ads
        - 50:4-3.20 Humorous
          See also: ADV 35:4-4, Comics; ADV 50:4-3.4, Cartoon and Comic Strip
        - 50:4-3.21 Length of Copy
        - 50:4-3.22 Military
          See also: MKT 70:2-1.1, Advertising to the Military
        - 50:4-3.23 Minorities/Ethnics in Copy/Commercials
        - [New Product--see: MKT 60:2-7, New Product Promotion]
        - 50:4-3.24 Newsletter Form
        - 50:4-3.25 Political
          See also: MKT 0:4, Metamarketing
        - [Positioning--see: MKT 5:2-9, Positioning; also, ADV 50:4-3.8, Comparative/Comparison Copy]
        - 50:4-3.26 Price
        - 50:4-3.27 Product
          See also: ADV 50:4-3.9.1, Corporate Image vs. Product Copy
          - 50:4-3.27.1 Technical Products
        - [Recruitment--see: ADV 50:4-3.7, Classified: Including Recruitment]
        - 50:4-3.28 Special Interest
        - 50:4-3.29 Testimonial/Endorser/Celebrities
        - 50:4-3.30 Townsend Points (Box 40)
        - 50:4-3.31 Trademarks in Copy
          See also: ADM 0:2-10.21, Logos, Slogans, Trade Characters/Names and Marks, Corporate; also ADM 0:2-10.9, Copyrights
        - 50:4-3.32 Women/Children/Models/Elderly in Copy/Commercials
      - 50:4-4 Copy: Copy/Message Testing and Research (includes information on copy claims/substantiation - pretest research)
      - 50:4-5 Copy: Copywriting
        See also: ADM 0:2-7.2.13.1, Technical Writing; ADM 0:2-7.2.13, Writing; ADV 5:10-3, Agency Creative Staff, N.E.C.
    - ADV 50:5 Media Buying, Evaluation, Planning and Selection
      See also: ADV 20, CAMPAIGN & MEDIA PLANNING, N.E.C.
      - 50:5-1 Media Buying, Evaluation, Planning and Selection, in combination or N.E.C.
      - 50:5-2 Checklists for (all media) Media Planners ( Media/Scope and others)
      - 50:5-3 Computers and Mathematical Models in the Media Planning/Selection Process
        See also: MKT 40:4-4, Computers in Marketing; MKT 40:4-5, Gaming and Modeling in Marketing: Theory and Commentary, N.E.C.; MKT 40:4-5.1, Modeling and Gaming Techniques Designed for Specific Marketing Application Decisions; MKT 50:2, Techniques of Marketing Research, all subsections, especially MKT 50:2-1.24, Linear and Non-Linear Programming
        - 50:5-3.1 Comparability/Standardization of Circulation (Audience/Universe) Data (Box 41)
          - 50:5-3.1.1 AIA (now B/PAA) Media Data Form Commentary
            - 50:5-3.1.1.1 MCC (Media Comparability Council) Information and Media Data Forms
          - 50:5-3.1.2 Suggested Media Data Forms, N.E.C.
      - 50:5-4 Media Buying, Evaluation, Planning and Selection Factors
        - 50:5-4.1 Media Buying, Evaluation, Planning and Selection Factors as Identified by Surveys (includes Folio: AdGuide)
        - 50:5-4.2 Circulation (Audience/Universe/Total Audience): Measurement and Research Concepts/Management and Principles
          - 50:5-4.2.1 ABP's Business Marketing Laboratory Study (The Ryan Study; The Syracuse Study), Findings and Commentary
            For information on the ABP/Taylor Instrument Company study of the business paper reading environment, see ADV 40:3-7.1
          - 50:5-4.2.2 Syndicated Audience Research (Simmons, TGI commentary/controversy/merger)
        - 50:5-4.3 Circulation (Audience/Universe): Auditing Bureaus (U.S./Canada)
          - 50:5-4.3.1 Audit Bureau of Circulations, (ABC), Functions, History, General Information, N.E.C.
            - 50:5-4.3.1.1 ABC, Guides to Using Reports
          - 50:5-4.3.2 Business Publications Audit of Circulation, Inc.. (BPA), Functions, History, General Information, N.E.C.
            - 50:5-4.3.2.1 BPA, Guides to Using Reports
              - 50:5-4.3.2.1.1 BPA, SMA (Selected Market Audit) Division
          - 50:5-4.3.3 Canadian Circulations Audit Board (CCAB)
          - 50:5-4.3.4 Verified Audit Circulation Corporation (VAC)
          - 50:5-4.3.5 Sworn Statements
          - 50:5-4.3.6 The Case for Audited Publications
        - 50:5-4.4 Circulation (Audience/Universe): Auditing Bureaus Around the World
        - 50:5-4.5 Association of National Advertisers (ANA) Magazine Circulation Rate Trends
        - 50:5-4.6 Circulation: Costs (CPM etc.)
          See also: ADV 50:55.1, Advertising Costs and Rates, particularly ADV 50:5-5.3.3.1, Rate Trends by Medium, Marketing & Media Decisions
        - 50:5-4.7 Circulation: Franchise Circulation
        - 50:5-4.8 Magazine Publishers Association (MPA): Circulations of Business Publication Members
        - 50:5-4.9 Circulation: Paid vs. Free, General Commentary
          See also: ADV 50:5-3.1, Comparability/Standardization of Circulation - Audience/Universe - Data
          - 50:5-4.9.1 Paid vs. Free Circulation, Tide series
        - [Circulation: Pass-Along--see: ADV 40:3-7.3, Pass-Along Reading]
        - 50:5-4.10 Circulation: Publication Distribution, N.E.C.
          - 50:5-4.10.1 Newsstand and Single Copy Sales
          - 50:5-4.10.2 Postal Service Problems (alternate delivery)
        - 50:5-4.11 Circulation: Reach and Frequency
          See also: ADV 50:5-3, Computers and Mathematical Models in the Media Planning/Selection Process; ADV 50:1, Concentration and Dominance; ADV 50:2, Continuity and Repetition in Advertising, all subsections particularly ADV 50:2-2, Frequency in Advertising; ADV 50:5-5.7, Frequency of Issue; MKT 65:5, Sources of Information of Purchasing Influences
        - [Circulation: Readership--see: ADV 40:3, Readership, all subsections]
        - 50:5-4.12 Circulation: Renewals
          See also: ADV 50 5-4.9, Circulation, Paid vs. Free; and ADV 50:5-4.9.1, Paid vs. Free, Tide series
        - 50:5-4.13 Circulation: Request
          See also: ADV 50:5-4.9, Circulation, Paid vs. Free; and ADV 50:5-4.9.1, Paid vs. Free, Tide series
        - 50:5-4.14 Circulation: SIC Analysis
          See also: ADV 50:5-3.1, Comparability/Standardization of Circulation - Audience/Universe - Data; MKT 50:2-4.4, SIC Analysis and Research
          - 50:5-4.14.1 Circulation: Subscription Sales (promotion, etc.)
        - 50:5-4.15 Circulation: Turnover: Men on the Move
          See also: ADM 0:2-8.21.13, Turnover
        - 50:5-4.16 Circulation: Unit Counts
      - 50:5-5 Media Buying, Evaluation, Planning and Selection Factors, Other Than Circulation (Audience/Universe) (Box 42)
        See also: ADV 35:1-3, Media, Business Papers costs and Economics of Business Paper Publishing, all subsections
        - 50:5-5.1 Advertising Costs and Rates, Discussions, N.E.C.
          See also: ADV 5:4-1.1, Barter and Brokerage of Media Space and Time
        - 50:5-5.2 Rate Discounting
        - 50:5-5.3 Rates/Costs Predictions and Indexes, Past, Present and Future, by Issuing Source, N.E.C.
          Selected examples from defunct publications or discontinued series are included to illustrate how the subject has been treated and to aid in the construction of indexes for post-WW II years; see also: ADV 55:3-2, Doyle Dane Bernbach: Media Trends.
          - 50:5-5.3.1 Ad Agency-Prepared Rates/Costs: Predictions and Indexes
          - 50:5-5.3.2 Association of National Advertisers, Inc. Circulation and Rate Trend Analyses, by Medium
            - 50:5-5.3.2.1 Business Publications
            - 50:5-5.3.2.2 Magazines
            - 50:5-5.3.2.3 Outdoor
            - 50:5-5.3.2.4 TV
          - 50:5-5.3.3 Rate Trends, Publication-Produced, by Medium
            - 50:5-5.3.3.1 Marketing & Media Decisions
            - 50:5-5.3.3.2 Media/Scope (discontinued)
            - 50:5-5.3.3.3 Printers' Ink (discontinued)
            - 50:5-5.3.3.4 Tide (discontinued)
            - 50:5-5.3.3.5 International Trade Press Cost Indexes
        - 50:5-5.4 Production Costs
        - 50:5-5.5 Rate Digests: McGraw-Hill Publications
        - 50:5-5.6 Editorial Evaluation
          See also: ADV 35:1-1.1, The Business Paper Editor/Editorial Integrity
        - 50:5-5.7 Frequency of Issue
          See also: ADV 50:2, Continuity and Repetition, all subsections especially ADV 50:2-2, Frequency in Advertising; ADV 50:5-4.11, Reach and Frequency
        - 50:5-5.8 New Medium Considerations
        - 50:5-5.9 Regional/Demographic Editions
        - 50:5-5.10 Media-Sponsored Research/Promotion
          - 50:5-5.10.1 Media-Sponsored Research/Promotion as a Media Analysis, Buying and Measurement Aid, N.E.C. (includes media presentations)
            See also: SAL 5:5, MEDIA SALESPERSONS
          - 50:5-5.10.2 Media-Sponsored Research: Circulation Promotion
          - 50:5-5.10.3 Media-Sponsored Research: Preference Studies
            See also: ADV 40:34.2, Readership Studies: Used or Misused? Pros and Cons
          - 50:5-5.10.4 Media-Sponsored Research: Promotion
          - 50:5-5.10.5 PIB Data: How They May Be Used By Magazines in Research/Promotion
          - 50:5-5.10.6 Suggested Standards/Disclosure Forms for Media Research
        - 50:5-5.11 Size of Issue (thick vs. thin) (Box 43)
          See also: ADV 40:3-5, Reader Traffic: Readership Levels Throughout a Publication; ADV 50:7-1, Position Values in Advertising, all subsections, particularly ADV 50:7-4, Position, Front vs. Back of Issue
        - 50:5-5.12 Special Issues, N.E.C. (includes information on buyers guides and show issues)
          See also: ADV 35:2-1.1, Directories
          - 50:5-5.12.1 Special Issues Planned, by year, by McGraw-Hill Publications (intermittent)
    - ADV 50:6 Merchandising
      See also: MKT 0:5, Retailing/Wholesaling/Merchandising
      - 50:6-1 Merchandising the Advertising Program, N.E.C.
      - 50:6-2 Merchandising to Distributors
        see also: MKT 20:9-6, Distributor Promotion
      - 50:6-3 Merchandising to Salespersons
    - ADV 50:7 Position
      - 50:7-1 Position Values in Advertising, N.E.C.
        See also: ADV 40:3-5, Reader Traffic: Readership Levels Throughout a Publication; ADV 50:5-5.11, Size of Issue: thick vs. thin
      - 50:7-2 Covers
      - 50:7-3 Effects of Accompanying Reading Matter (e.g. readership of advertisements facing editorial vs. those in solid advertising sections)
      - 50:7-4 Front vs. Back of Issue (note see alsos listed under ADV 50:7-1)
      - 50:7-5 Multiple Insertions in Same Issue
        See also: ADV 50:1-2, Dominance: Impact Advertising, and subsection
      - 50:7-6 Right vs. Left Hand Pages
      - 50:7-7 Spread vs. Bunched (What kind of publication format is better for advertisers/readers: solid ad section or even mixture of ads and editorial?)
        See also: ADV 50:7-3, Effects of Accompanying Reading Matter
    - ADV 50:8 Size of Space
      - 50:8-1 Analyses of Space Units in Business Publications (most-frequently used ad sizes)
      - 50:8-2 Fractional vs. Full Page(s): Readership/Attention-Value Relationships (includes information on horizontal vs. vertical)
      - 50:8-3 Inserts and Spreads (includes information on multipages)
        See also: ADV 35:4-8.1, Newspapers, Supplements
      - 50:8-4 Page Size (total area) ( Reader's Digest studies)
      - 50:8-5 Small-Space Advertising
        See also: ADV 50:1-2.1, Answers to the Question: Big Ads Seldom ... Small Ads Often?
    - ADV 50:9 Visual Presentation
      - 50:9-1 Ad Characteristics (size, color, illustrations, and other elements in combination or N.E.C.) Answers to the Question: What Are the Characteristics of Well-Read Advertisements? (includes information on free-form ads, etc., and standardization of format/layout, umbrella advertisements)
      - 50:9-2 Bleed
      - 50:9-3 Color
      - 50:9-4 Graphic Arts (reproduction processes) Developments
        - 50:9-4.1 Typography/Graphics Technology
          See also: ADV 50:9-12, Reverse Plate
      - 50:9-5 Headlines/Coverlines/Advertising Slogans
        See also: ADM 0:2-10.21, Logos, Slogans, Trade Characters/Names and Marks: Corporate
      - 50:9-6 Illustrations
        See also: ADV 50:9-8, Photographs vs. Artwork
      - 50:9-7 Microencapsulation (for adding aromatic dimension to ads)
      - 50:9-8 Photographs vs. Artwork
        See also: ADV 5:9-6, Illustrations
      - 50:9-9 Product Picture
      - 50:9-10 Products Featured (number in ad)
      - 50:9-11 Re-Use of Ad Elements (to create basic ads and to control costs)
      - 50:9-12 Reverse Plate
        See also: ADV 50:9-4.1, Typography/Graphics Technology
      - 50:9-13 Shape of Ad
        See also: ADV 50:8-2, Fractional vs. Full Page(s)
      - 50:9-14 Subliminal Advertising
      - 50:9-15 Visual and Other Autonomic Measures (tachistoscope testing, pupil dilation, etc.)
        See also: MKT 50:2-1.48, VOPAN - Voice Pitch Analysis/Brain Wave Analysis
  - ADV 55. ADVERTISING VOLUME, Expenditures in Major Media (Box 44)
    In 1968, the Index-Developer put together a listing of sources publishing advertising volume data and the major reports published by these sources. The identified reports numbered nearly one hundred and covered broadcast media, business publications, farm and general magazines, direct mail, newspapers, outdoor, point-of-purchase, and transit advertising; too, there was a goodly helping of entries covering such specialties as life insurance advertising volume by medium, city and area development advertising, resort and tourist advertising expenditures, bank advertising expenditures, liquor advertising expenditures, and so on. However, during the past fifteen years (circa 1970-1985) the Marketing Information Center rarely, if ever, received requests for any of these published statistics. In this listing, therefore, only those sources and figures for which the MIC receives most inquiries are cited. This listing is geared strictly to the expressed needs of the businesspaper advertiser.
    For the advertising scholar, though, a sampling of historic and one-of-a-kind volume reports are given headings (together with a thumbnail commentary). These historic statistics may be useful to researchers curious to learn how volume estimates were compiled and presented in the old days. It is interesting, for example, to compare the variations in advertising volume data compiled by Charles Yang and others for Advertising Age from 1965 to 1971 with those compiled by Robert J. Coen (who continued the pioneering work of the late Dr. L.D.H. Weld) for Printers' Ink - Marketing/Communications and now featured by Advertising Age. Also, it may be of value to some ad volume researchers to learn how business publication statistics were compiled by Angelo R. Venezian for Industrial Marketing (now Business Marketing) and how and why the earlier post-World War II business paper statistics were adjusted by their compiler and were subsequently updated by the American Business Press, Inc. Examples of these older studies (on occasion, the complete series) are on file within the Marketing Information Center.
    See also: IOP 10:2-10, World Advertising Expenditures, and subsections.
    - ADV 55:1 Business Publications
      See also: ADV 55:3-1, Advertising Age, Forecasts and Historical Statistics as prepared by Robert J. Coen, for additional business publication dollar volume estimates - past and present; additionally, see ADV 55:3-2, Doyle Dane Bernbach: Media Trends, the Business Press Advertising Trends section, and ADV 35:4-6.4, The Folio 400 and Commentary, especially the Folio 400 Business Magazines section)
      - 55:1-1 American Business Press, Inc. Annual Dollar and Page Volume Estimates
        These figures may be obtained by contacting the association. They are a continuation of those originally developed by the McGraw-Hill Marketing Information Center for Angelo R. Venezian for publication in his annual Industrial Marketing (IM)- now Business Marketing article on the state of the business press. The Angelo Venezian articles - see ADV 55:1-2.2 - were featured in IM starting in January, 1947 and concluding in November, 1964. AV took over authorship of the studies in June 1965 and the last article type study in IM - under the byline of John B. Babcock - was in June, 1966. For a while thereafter the ABP published the studies as an insert in IM under the bannerline ABP Info/File. The last ABP Info/File appeared in 1974 and covered 1973 data. For many years, ABP-produced basic business publication data, including ad volume statistics, were featured in a series of foldout leaflets and/or booklets titled Fast Facts - see following subsections.
        - 55:1-1.1 ABP Fast Facts (historic, discontinued; examples only; see preceding entry for historical notes)
        - 55:1-1.2 ABP Info/File (historic, discontinued; see ADV 55:1-1 for historical notes; includes the two Industrial Marketing articles mentioned in the historical notes)
        - 55:1-1.3 ABP Leading Advertisers in Business Publications (historic, discontinued; this series was first published in 1951 and was, discontinued after the 23rd annual survey - the 1973 edition)
        - 55:1-1.4 ABP Suggested Guidelines for Reporting Ad Volume (includes commentary on the Guidelines)
      - 55:1-2 Business Marketing (formerly Industrial Marketing), N.E.C.
        - 55:1-2.1 Ad Volume in Business Publications (quarterly and annual page totals by publication)
        - 55:1-2.2 Forecasts and Historical Statistics
          Annual articles authored by Angelo R. Venezian commencing January, 1947 and ending November, 1964; see ADV 55:1-1 for brief commentary on the history of this series. The Venezian statistics form the foundation of all those emanating from the ABP. An Index-Developer historical note: Mr. Venezian in his last - 1964 - study adjusted all his prior years' (1945-1963) dollar volume statistics.
          These adjusted figures have always been used by the ABP in their continuing compilations; ad volume researchers must be aware of this multi-year adjustment if they are exploring post-World War II trends; it is quite possible that such researchers might unwittingly use the unadjusted earlier statistics and become alarmed at apparent discrepancies in figures when comparing them with, say, modern ABP releases which feature the adjusted totals.
        - 55:1-2.3 100 Largest Advertisers in Business Publications (derived from The Rome Report data)
          - 55:1-2.3.1 Ad Spending by Market (derived from The Rome Report data)
        - 55:1-2.4 Commentary on Declining Ad Volume (includes observations on the year's hot trade magazines which occasionally form part of the commentaries)
      - 55:1-3 The Gallagher Report: Annual Business Publications Scorecard (this series was once semi-annual; first published circa 1960; top one hundred publications tabulations - one for gross ad revenues, the other for advertising pages)
      - 55:1-4 McGraw-Hill Publications Company: Competing Advertising Data; known in-company as the green sheet (confidential monthly compilations - dating back to the mid-1930s - of page volume of McGraw-Hill publications and their major competitors; monthly and cumulative totals, share of market, comparisons with comparable previous-year periods, etc.)
        - 55:1-4.1 McGraw-Hill Publications Company: Company and Product Advertising Analyses (Discontinued; historic examples only. The Company and Product Advertising Analyses provided, in two volumes, a complete information file on competitive advertising data; advertising schedules -pages and dollars - were indicated for over 20,000 firms in approximately 200 business publications. Volume II was the product section - tabulations showing, for 700-plus products, schedules [publication, pages and dollars] being used to advertise those products)
      - 55:1-5 Printers' Ink (which changed its name to Marketing/Communications before being discontinued): Page Volume by Publication (historic; examples only)
      - 55:1-6 The Rome Report of Business Publication Advertising (semi-annual compilations of the advertising appearing in approximately 500 - number varies by year - business publications; lists advertisers in alphabetical order, the publications scheduled, the total space run and the dollar expenditure in each publication and in total; for a time, this series of reports was published under the Media Records banner)
      - 55:1-7 Other Business Publication Ad Volume Estimates and Commentary (From time to time an investigating source, a magazine as often as not, takes statistics from a compiling source, such as the Rome Report, and works up top ten or top one hundred listings of advertisers [see also: ADV 55:1-2.3, Business Marketing, 100 Largest Advertisers in Business Publications are subsequently published in a variety of formats and commented on. This heading takes in these usually irregularly-published treatises.)
    - [Direct Mail Advertising Volume--see: ADV 35:3-14, DM Volume]
    - ADV 55:2 General Magazines
      See also: ADV 55:3, Multi-Media Expenditures, as many tabulations in that section include overall general magazine expenditure statistics; for example, the R.J. Coen/ Advertising Age multi-media compilations include general magazine figures, and occasional AA summary reports take these data back into the 1930s.
      - 55:2-1 Advertising Age: Advertising Pages for U.S., Canadian and Foreign Consumer Publications (current month and cumulative)
        - 55:2-1.1 Advertising Age: The Top (#) Magazine Advertisers (occasional compilations)
      - [ Folio--see: ADV 35:4-6.4, The Folio 400]
      - 55:2-2 The Gallagher Report: Annual Consumer Magazine Advertising Scorecard (top one hundred publications tabulations - one for advertising revenue, the other for advertising pages)
      - 55:2-3 Printers' Ink (discontinued) (magazine ad-page volume; series published for the last time in PI's December 18, 1964 issue; historic examples only)
        - 55:2-3.1 Printers' Ink (discontinued): 150 Leading Magazine Advertisers of (year) (historic examples only)
      - 55:2-4 Publishers Information Bureau (This organization publishes a whole host of statistics on general magazine advertising and offers access to its data base. It is suggested that the full menu of services be obtained from the Bureau. The Marketing Information Center received questions directed in the main to the following services.)
        - 55:2-4.1 Magazine Totals
        - 55:2-4.2 Class Totals
        - 55:2-4.3 Brand Index
        - 55:2-4.4 Brand Detail, all sections
      - 55:2-5 The Rome Report of Expenditures in International Media (semi-annual compilation of advertising activity in approximately 450 - number varies from year-to-year - international and regional general business and news publications; features information by company, expenditures by broad product category, space run by publication year-to-date)
    - ADV 55:3 Multi-Media Expenditures
      - 55:3-1 Advertising Age: forecasts and historical statistics, as prepared by Robert J. Coen